<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engineerette</title>
    <description>Engineering survival guide</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:07:14 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:07:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Top Skills That Engineer Consultants Should Have</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re a fresh engineering graduate or a seasoned engineer, consulting firms have something for everyone. Engineering consultants are exposed to a variety of projects in a short time. This provides learning opportunities for junior designers and a dynamic environment for senior engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 22:19:52 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/top-skills-that-engineer-consultants-should-have/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/top-skills-that-engineer-consultants-should-have/</guid>
        
        <tag>Consulting</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Impressive Questions to Ask in a Job Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Interviews are a two-way street. The final part of an interview perfectly embodies this philosophy. Almost all recruiters close off an interview by asking the interviewee if they have any questions. It is the final opportunity for you to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leave a lasting impression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;find out if you’re a good fit for the team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;catch potential &lt;a href=&quot;/red-flags-in-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;red flags&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-ask-smart-questions-to-ask-at-the-end-of-a-job-interview&quot;&gt;How to ask smart questions to ask at the end of a job interview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most job seekers are relieved to hear a recruiter ask, “do you have any questions for us?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may signal the end of your interview, you shouldn’t let your guard down yet. The questions you ask the recruiter can impact the success of your interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst response you can say is no. It shows a lack of interest, and many recruiters will notice. Having smart questions prepared is crucial. Remember, this is the last opportunity to impress and figure out whether or not you are a good fit for the role. Take advantage of this last chance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoid-asking-standard-questions&quot;&gt;Avoid asking standard questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many job candidates will ask standard questions about the job, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you describe a typical day of work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where do you see the company in five years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the company values?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there opportunities to progress?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is your favourite thing about working at the company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the office culture like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the next steps of the hiring process?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you describe the team I will be working with?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will I be required to go through any training before starting work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are informative but also a little boring. Your interviewer has likely been asked these questions by the other candidates already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out more about certain aspects of the company, take this chance to ask away. However, don’t ask these questions for the sake of asking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impress-your-interviewers-with-thoughtful-questions&quot;&gt;Impress your interviewers with thoughtful questions&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 13:35:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/impressive-questions-to-ask-in-a-job-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/impressive-questions-to-ask-in-a-job-interview/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technical Issues During Online Exams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Exam season has always been stressful. With schools migrating online, exams have followed suit. Now on top of regular exam anxiety, there’s also additional stress from online testing and remote proctoring. With the added layer of technology between you and your exam, more things can go wrong.  For this reason, some students feel more nervous about an online exam.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 19:50:34 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/technical-issues-during-online-exams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/technical-issues-during-online-exams/</guid>
        
        <tag>Grades</tag>
        
        
        <category>School Survival</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Perfectionist Students Struggle in the Workplace</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Perfectionism is a double-edged sword. On one hand, perfectionists create high-quality outputs and hard workers. On the other hand, perfectionists struggle with impossible expectations and finite resources. While school may be forgiving to negative perfectionist tendencies, the workplace is not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 12:56:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/why-perfectionist-students-struggle-in-the-workplace/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/why-perfectionist-students-struggle-in-the-workplace/</guid>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        <tag>Growing Up</tag>
        
        
        <category>School Survival</category>
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Ace Technical Engineering Interviews</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every engineering job requires different sets of technical skills and experiences. Employers use technical interviews to assess and scope out their best job candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 23:56:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technical Assessment Styles in Engineering Interviews</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Technical interviews gauge a job candidate’s technical skills. Every engineering jobs require different skills, and so every interview is unique. Despite this, all technical interviews are essentially a series of assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 23:32:21 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/technical-assessment-styles-in-engineering-interviews/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/technical-assessment-styles-in-engineering-interviews/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Audience Expertise Categories in Technical Communication</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re writing a client report, selling yourself during an &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt;, or presenting to executives, understanding your audience’s technical level is crucial for technical communications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 20:11:32 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/</guid>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Professional Voicemail Greeting Guide for Job Seekers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this day and age of instant messaging, phone calls have fallen out of fashion. Despite this, many recruiters still contact job candidates by phone. This is why you should include your phone number on your resume. However, simply listing a phone number is not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 21:40:52 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/professional-voicemail-greeting-guide-for-job-seekers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/professional-voicemail-greeting-guide-for-job-seekers/</guid>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        <tag>Etiquette</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Feeling Lost After Graduation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We spend nearly two decades in school to prep for the “real world”. When we finally graduate, we’re eager to jump in and tackle whatever life throws at us. However once the initial excitement wears off, some new grads find themselves lost and disoriented.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 21:51:32 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/feeling-lost-after-graduation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/feeling-lost-after-graduation/</guid>
        
        <tag>Growing Up</tag>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        <tag>Relationships</tag>
        
        
        <category>Personal Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Harsh Realities of Job Security in Engineering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Job security can provide steady income, give peace of mind, and improve quality of life. Thus, many people will naturally gravitate towards careers that seem stable. For some, a career in engineering comes to mind. But is engineering as secure as it seems?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:30:12 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/the-harsh-realities-of-job-security-in-engineering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/the-harsh-realities-of-job-security-in-engineering/</guid>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        <tag>Money</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
