<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engineerette</title>
    <description>Engineering survival guide</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:26:30 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:26:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>No Dream Job, No Problem!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a popular saying, “Choose a job you love, and you will never have to work a day in your life.” But what if you never find your true calling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pressured-to-find-your-passion&quot;&gt;Pressured to find your passion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimistic-career-guidance-in-school&quot;&gt;Optimistic career guidance in school&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In school, we’re asked about our dream jobs. Teachers introduce us to personality quizzes, like Myers-Briggs types and personality colors, which will recommend you a career path on completion. These exercises induce self-reflection and are meant to guide us in pursuing our passions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, you may have felt excited to discover your passion. But that anticipation was replaced by worry as years go by and you still haven’t decided on a dream career. Graduation is fast approaching, and many are forced to decide whether they are ready or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hustle-culture-at-work&quot;&gt;Hustle culture at work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hustle culture, job dissatisfaction and complacency are viewed as a source of shame. Thus, most people won’t admit that they don’t feel passion for their jobs. Even after colleagues leave, most avoid burning bridges so they rarely admit to disinterest in their work. 
These environmental factors leave you with an echo chamber where everyone gushes about how much they love their job. While some may be genuine, it makes it seem like everyone has their life figured out when that is simply not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;crumbling-dream-job-fantasy&quot;&gt;Crumbling dream job fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;practical-concerns&quot;&gt;Practical concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, we have hobbies, but there are other factors to consider beyond interest, like employability, stability, talent, and compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every passion can be monetized. Even when they can be, the path can be quite challenging. It can potentially take a lot of time and luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are more risk-averse, you may feel more comfortable prioritizing practicality over passion. Sometimes, this means putting aside passions as a side-hustle, at least for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prioritizing-yourself-in-a-work-centric-world&quot;&gt;Prioritizing yourself in a work-centric world&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigating in hustle culture is tricky when you don’t love your jobs. It’s important to look after yourself. 
There are a few paths forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-fake-the-passion&quot;&gt;1. Fake the passion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of companies that will pay you big bucks to work on something you might not believe in. Some of these companies also go hard on selling the corporate Kool-Aid. If you don’t openly express loving your work, you aren’t getting promoted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feigning enthusiasm can be quite soul-crushing, but you may feel tempted to tough it out if the practical benefits are worth it. This can be an appealing option for young professionals looking to maximize their income and accelerate their careers. And who knows, maybe if you drink enough corporate Kool-Aid, you’ll start to believe in the company’s mission?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you can’t bring yourself to genuinely believe in the company’s mission, this option is not sustainable and can lead to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-set-boundaries-and-collect-pay-cheques&quot;&gt;2. Set boundaries and collect pay cheques&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel indifferent about your work but are content with the lifestyle your day job provides you, is there really anything wrong? Hustle culture is one big rat race and it’s easy to get swept up in competition. If your needs are met, there’s no need to strive for more. Spare yourself from corporate cringe and enjoy your life outside of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you draw a clear line between your personal life and work, you have a lot more time to do what you actually like to do. Whether it’s spending time with loved ones, taking up hobbies, or growing a side-hustle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-find-a-new-job&quot;&gt;3. Find a new job&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realizing you hate your job is a hard pill to swallow. Changing your situation is an even bigger hurdle to get over. Change is scary, thus many jobs are called “golden handcuffs”. Individuals who’ve already sunk a ton of resources into their current careers will likely find it harder to justify a career change. However, experiences and skills are actually quite transferable, as long as you spin them the right way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No job is worth your mental health.  If you dread showing up for work every day and daydream about “what-ifs”, maybe it’s time to make a move to something you’ll like a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a clue what your next move should be, don’t sweat it! The goal should be to do something you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; hate. Ask yourself, “what aspects of your current role do you dislike?”, and work from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding a career you can work with can be an iterative process, and we should recognize it as so. Let’s start by shedding the false perception of “instantly clicking” and falling in love with a dream job.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 22:10:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/no-dream-job-no-problem/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/no-dream-job-no-problem/</guid>
        
        <tag>Growing Up</tag>
        
        <tag>Money</tag>
        
        <tag>Passion</tag>
        
        <tag>Office Culture</tag>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        
        <category>Personal Life</category>
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Quit a Job Professionally</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Quitting a job can be an incredibly liberating experience or a bittersweet one. It depends on how much you enjoyed your job. Regardless of how you truly feel, it’s important to leave on a good note. After all, you never know when you may run into your colleagues again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-resign-from-your-job-gracefully&quot;&gt;How to resign from your job gracefully&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-confirm-details-with-your-next-employer-if-you-have-one&quot;&gt;1. Confirm details with your next employer if you have one&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not always have the next step lined up in your career, but if you do, make sure you have it in the bag before you start making moves to quitting your current job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-clear-any-personal-items-from-your-professional-workspace&quot;&gt;2. Clear any personal items from your professional workspace&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some circumstances, you may be asked to leave immediately after you inform the company of your plans to quit. To save yourself from potential complications in the future, be prepared to turn over all your company belongings right away. If you have any personal items left behind in your office or computer, it may not be easy for you to retrieve them later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-speak-to-your-boss-about-your-plan-to-quit&quot;&gt;3. Speak to your boss about your plan to quit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re ready to give your notice, set up a meeting with your direct manager. During the meeting, be direct and professional. Let them know that you’re planning to give your notice of resignation, but you wanted to let them know first. They may ask you why or try to change your mind. You aren’t obligated to give a reason or justify your decisions if you don’t want to. However, if you do, try not to sound too negative or complain-y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-give-written-notice&quot;&gt;4. Give written notice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a brief email stating that you are providing written notice of your resignation and the day you plan on leaving. You may also choose to express your gratitude for the time you spent at the company with one or two sentences. Additionally, provide non-work contact information in case they need to reach you. In general, you’ll want to keep this email short, professional, and generally positive. Don’t forget to proofread your email! It also helps to CC yourself and the HR team so that everyone has a record of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-be-proactive-with-a-transition-plan&quot;&gt;5. Be proactive with a transition plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As tempting as it may be to forget about all your projects, the last days of work are paramount to leaving on good terms. If your manager has not reached out to you already, be proactive and reach out to them to ask how you should carry out the turnover. Your team will certainly appreciate this. This will also give you a good opportunity to let the rest of your team know about your planned departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-tell-colleagues-gracefully&quot;&gt;6. Tell colleagues gracefully&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking the news to your colleagues requires tact. Your colleagues could react to this update in many different ways. Some will ask why, others will ask where you’re headed, and a few might even complain about the company and express interest in leaving as well! No matter the reaction, try to keep the interactions positive and avoid speaking poorly about the company. Again, you aren’t required to share details if you don’t feel comfortable doing so. Try to focus on the good times you’ve had at the company and the adventures you are looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-avoid-excessively-complaining-during-exit-interviews&quot;&gt;7. Avoid excessively complaining during exit interviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most companies will conduct an exit interview before your last day. They are looking for feedback and how they can improve. Again, you are not obligated to share anything. It may be tempting to rant about everything, but that’s not the way to go. If you choose to share your feedback, stick to one or two key areas for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-send-goodbye-email-with-an-invitation-to-keep-in-touch&quot;&gt;8. Send goodbye email with an invitation to keep in touch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your last day of work, send an email to your colleagues announcing your departure. Keep it short and sweet. Express gratitude for your time together with everyone and invite your team to stay in touch. Don’t forget to provide a method of contact! This could be anything from an email, phone number, or social media. This email is best sent at the beginning or middle of the day so people have time to respond and say goodbye. It’s also helpful to CC your personal email so you can also have a record of their emails in case you ever need to reach out to them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 23:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/how-to-quit-a-job-professionally/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/how-to-quit-a-job-professionally/</guid>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        <tag>Etiquette</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anxiety from Sending Emails</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing business emails can be quite stressful. Professionals breaking into the office workplace often experience anxiety while sending emails. Many overthink basic email etiquette and ponder trivial word choices. This anxiety is a minor inconvenience at most, but if you’ve ever experienced this, you would know that it can be quite mentally taxing and time-consuming to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stressing-over-trivial-details-while-writing-emails&quot;&gt;Stressing over trivial details while writing emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever typed up an email to your boss, professor, or hiring manager, you’re likely all too familiar with the dreaded “email sending anxiety”. It usually happens when you’re sending an important email or if your recipient is someone you want to impress. You worry over every minor detail and stress over trivial matters like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What email greeting should I use? Is “Hi” too casual? Is “Dear” too old-fashioned?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I address the recipient? Full name? Title? To Whom It May Concern?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How should I sign-off my email? Is “Best Regards” too generic?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does my email strike a good balance between friendly and professional?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is my writing style going to get the intended tone across?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should I use an emoji if they sent one to me last time?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should I reply all?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is my message even important enough for an email? Should I just call instead?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You find yourself obsessively re-reading your message, overthinking every single word. Only after you’ve exhausted all your energy proof-reading, do you finally hit send.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You check the clock and see that half an hour has passed. Thirty minutes to write two pathetic sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/sidecanvas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/content/EmailAnxiety.png&quot; alt=&quot;Anxiety from sending emails webcomic&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Email anxiety webcomic, from sidecanvas &lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-stop-overthinking-emails&quot;&gt;How to stop overthinking emails?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-realize-that-emails-are-just-emails&quot;&gt;1. Realize that emails are… just emails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many situations where email sending anxiety can arise. In each situation, the main cause of stress can be boiled down to the fear of looking stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When writing to our superiors, we feel the need to craft the absolute perfect email. We want to show our competency and shine bright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing proper emails is important, but there is no need to pull your hair out trying to write a masterpiece. Even if you read over it a hundred times and optimize your word choice to get just the right tone across, it’s just an email at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-practice-writing&quot;&gt;2. Practice writing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to stop overthinking, you need to accept the reality that nobody else is overanalyzing your emails. That being said, it’s certainly easier said than done. Fortunately, the more emails you send, the easier it becomes over time. You’ll become faster at writing and hone your proofreading skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you gradually refine your writing style, professional emails will begin to feel more natural and come second-nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-read-from-the-perspective-of-the-recipient&quot;&gt;3. Read from the perspective of the recipient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of overcoming email sending anxiety, reading other people’s emails can help a lot as well. Not only can you pick up some handy writing tricks, but you also get to read from the eyes of a recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepping into the shoes of the reader, you can fully grasp just how little attention you pay to the details that others put in their emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a reader, you’re more focused on the main point. If the sender put any extra thought and detail into their message, you probably didn’t even notice it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep this perspective in mind next time you’re scratching your head about the most polite email salutations or the friendliest email sign-offs. Just pick something simple and move along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-focus-on-the-mistakes-that-matter&quot;&gt;4. Focus on the mistakes that matter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of focusing on trivial details, it’s important to put your full attention on what people do notice: embarrassing typos and other glaring errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is their name spelt correctly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is your name spelt correctly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you sending it to the right recipient?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the company name right?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you remember to include the attachment? Is it the right attachment?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mistakes are more noticeable but are luckily easier to catch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to read over your email a hundred times. Just once or twice is enough, but you need to make sure you give it your full attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read every single word. Check every attachment. Verify all the recipients and CCs are correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the worst mistakes can slip right under our noses and it happens because we didn’t focus on what mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 19:19:52 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/anxiety-from-sending-emails/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anxiety-from-sending-emails/</guid>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        <tag>Etiquette</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Top Skills That Engineer Consultants Should Have</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re a fresh engineering graduate or a seasoned engineer, consulting firms have something for everyone. Engineering consultants are exposed to a variety of projects in a short time. This provides learning opportunities for junior designers and a dynamic environment for senior engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a new graduate looking to become a consultant engineer, be sure to check out &lt;a href=&quot;/5-things-every-junior-engineering-consultant-should-know/&quot;&gt;the top 5 things every junior engineering consultant should know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;skills-needed-to-succeed-as-a-consultant-engineer&quot;&gt;Skills needed to succeed as a consultant engineer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technical-flexibility&quot;&gt;Technical flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations often hire engineering consultants for their specialized knowledge and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineering consulting firms need to have both the depth and breadth of technical expertise to support all their various clients effectively. This expectation also extends to their team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In university, you likely specialized in one or two focused areas. In the world of engineering consulting, you will need to dip your toes into areas you’ve never covered at school. It can be daunting for new engineering graduates, but there is nothing to worry about. All engineer consultants start somewhere, and the workplace a great teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be thrown into projects you’ve never seen before. It’s wise to keep an open mind about what you’re working on because it won’t always be familiar. These situations can be stressful, but they are also a valuable learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-management&quot;&gt;Time management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations hire engineering consultants because it’s more cost-effective than hiring, training, and paying additional in-house staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consultant, you’re selling your time. The more hours you work, the more you charge your client. While it may seem like you are in control of how much you work, that is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clients often have expectations of how much they can pay their consultants. If the time you charge goes over their budget, it will certainly raise questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this, consultants need to be aware of how much time they are charging to projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-minded&quot;&gt;Business Minded&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When consultants plan projects and prepare quotes, they need to estimate working time and cost accurately to avoid complications down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you overestimate your quote, then you might lose your bid and a potential client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you underestimate your quote, then you might not be making any profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good consultant understands the needs of their clients and market demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strong-communicator&quot;&gt;Strong Communicator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good engineer consultants are also good collaborators, and thus you need strong communication skills to perform well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consultant, you will run into people with various technical backgrounds. When getting ideas across, an expert consultant caters their communication style to their &lt;a href=&quot;/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/&quot;&gt;audience’s expertise level&lt;/a&gt;. Different audience expertise level calls for a different communication style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re describing a solution to another engineer or pitching an idea to a client, you need to be aware of how you express yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 22:19:52 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/top-skills-that-engineer-consultants-should-have/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/top-skills-that-engineer-consultants-should-have/</guid>
        
        <tag>Consulting</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Impressive Questions to Ask in a Job Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Interviews are a two-way street. The final part of an interview perfectly embodies this philosophy. Almost all recruiters close off an interview by asking the interviewee if they have any questions. It is the final opportunity for you to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leave a lasting impression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;find out if you’re a good fit for the team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;catch potential &lt;a href=&quot;/red-flags-in-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;red flags&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-ask-smart-questions-to-ask-at-the-end-of-a-job-interview&quot;&gt;How to ask smart questions to ask at the end of a job interview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most job seekers are relieved to hear a recruiter ask, “do you have any questions for us?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may signal the end of your interview, you shouldn’t let your guard down yet. The questions you ask the recruiter can impact the success of your interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst response you can say is no. It shows a lack of interest, and many recruiters will notice. Having smart questions prepared is crucial. Remember, this is the last opportunity to impress and figure out whether or not you are a good fit for the role. Take advantage of this last chance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoid-asking-standard-questions&quot;&gt;Avoid asking standard questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many job candidates will ask standard questions about the job, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you describe a typical day of work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where do you see the company in five years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the company values?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there opportunities to progress?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is your favourite thing about working at the company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the office culture like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the next steps of the hiring process?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you describe the team I will be working with?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will I be required to go through any training before starting work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are informative but also a little boring. Your interviewer has likely been asked these questions by the other candidates already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out more about certain aspects of the company, take this chance to ask away. However, don’t ask these questions for the sake of asking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impress-your-interviewers-with-thoughtful-questions&quot;&gt;Impress your interviewers with thoughtful questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughtful questions are more interesting and unique. When done correctly, they can leave a good impression on your interviewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking generic questions that can apply to any job and company, show that you are serious by asking specific questions that demonstrate your interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem like a lot of work, but it’s easier than it sounds. The trick is to follow this simple format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elements of an impressive question&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledge a fact about the company or job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask a question about the fact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as that. By prefacing a question with extra facts, the question becomes an opportunity to show off what you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impress the interviewer by making callbacks to the information mentioned earlier in the interview and research your facts ahead of time. It shows that you have been attentive during the interview and have done your homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples-of-smart-questions-to-ask&quot;&gt;Examples of smart questions to ask&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the format described above, you can create customized questions to ask your interviewer without too much effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of calling back to previously mentioned information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You said that you have been working at the company for over ten years. In your opinion, where do you see the company in another ten years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You mentioned that you started working here as an engineering graduate. How has the company support your career growth?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earlier, you said that I would be working with your team. Could you describe what the team is like and the office culture?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You mentioned earlier that you had specialized in fluid dynamics in university. How has your specialization contributed to your work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As you said earlier, the next round is the technical assessment. May I ask when you are planning to notify the successful candidates from this round?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of demonstrating your knowledge of the job and company&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I know that the company takes both quality and safety very seriously. What strategies does your team use to meet both standards without using too many resources?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given that the company has been operating for over 75 years, what would you say are the benefits of working at an older, more established company versus a younger company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The job posting had mentioned flexible hours. Could you please describe what a typical day is like for a member of your team?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company has been recognized as one of the best places to work. Could you please tell me more about the office culture?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read on the news that the company is planning to expand into the renewable energy sector. Will your team be supporting this expansion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon closer inspection, you’ll notice that the questions asked are quite generic. What makes these questions stand out compared to their standard counterparts is the extra details. Tailor your questions with some prior research and attentive listening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 13:35:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/impressive-questions-to-ask-in-a-job-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/impressive-questions-to-ask-in-a-job-interview/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technical Issues During Online Exams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Exam season has always been stressful. With schools migrating online, exams have followed suit. Now on top of regular exam anxiety, there’s also additional stress from online testing and remote proctoring. With the added layer of technology between you and your exam, more things can go wrong.  For this reason, some students feel more nervous about an online exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reducing-the-risk-of-technical-issues-on-your-exam-day&quot;&gt;Reducing the risk of technical issues on your exam day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a test online can feel weird, especially if it’s your first time. Unfortunately higher levels of stress can negatively impact your exam performance. Therefore, it’s wise to be prepared for potential stressors that come with virtual exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-anxiety&quot;&gt;Tech Anxiety&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest downsides of taking exams online is its reliance on technology. If you’ve ever dealt with IT issues before, you would know that they’re incredibly annoying to deal with. It’s even more frustrating when your exam is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual proctors or exam delivery systems can experience technical issues of their own, and that is unavoidable. However, between the exam platform and you, it’s far more likely that the technical issues would come from your end. Even then, the chance of IT issues can be minimized with preparation and equipment testing ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks before your exam, read through the instructions provided. Online exams often provide instructions on what to do prior to and on your scheduled exam date. A few weeks may seem unnecessary but if you discover that your IT setup is insufficient, you will want that extra time to get your workspace in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common IT requirements for online exams include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fast internet (preferably wired)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no separate monitors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no remote connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no virtual machines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;webcam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;microphone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proctoring software installed ahead of time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;browser requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;operating system requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RAM requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;screen resolution requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CPU requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;administrator permissions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there’s a lot of requirements to review and it’s easy to miss something. Dedicate some time to go through the instructions, it could potentially save you a lot of stress down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some exam platforms offer a one-click equipment check. If your exam platform offers this feature, be sure to take advantage of it. While these tests do not guarantee a smooth exam day, they do a decent job of flagging potential insufficiencies in your setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of your exam, restart your computer. In fact, it’s good practice to reboot your machine regularly. This frees up memory space, clears temporary files, and can improve performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if-technical-issues-happen-during-the-online-exam&quot;&gt;What if technical issues happen during the online exam?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exam platforms often come with fail-safe designs. For example, some platforms auto-save answers as you write. Thus even if you disconnect without submitting, your answers are saved. That being said, it’s still good practice to save your work regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some systems also employ various protocols in the event of an IT issue. For instance, some institutions allow you to complete the remainder of your exam offline. Other institutions may require you to re-write your exam in another sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each institution runs differently so check with your exam issuer ahead of time for their procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If technical issues do arise during your exam, it’s not the end of the world. Technical issues are a part of our modern lives now and can happen at the worst times. The best we can do is flag potential issues ahead of time and prepare accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 19:50:34 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/technical-issues-during-online-exams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/technical-issues-during-online-exams/</guid>
        
        <tag>Grades</tag>
        
        
        <category>School Survival</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Perfectionist Students Struggle in the Workplace</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Perfectionism is a double-edged sword. On one hand, perfectionists create high-quality outputs and hard workers. On the other hand, perfectionists struggle with impossible expectations and finite resources. While school may be forgiving to negative perfectionist tendencies, the workplace is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-two-factors-that-encourage-perfectionism&quot;&gt;The two factors that encourage perfectionism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into a perfectionist’s struggle, we must first understand where it stems from. Different environments encourage different personality types. Perfectionism often shines in the presence of two main conditions: attainable perfection and infinite resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-attainable-perfection&quot;&gt;1. Attainable perfection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfectionists will only be satisfied when they achieve perfection. When perfection isn’t defined or attainable, they will always find flaws in their work. Perfectionists thrive when given concrete and attainable goals to work towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-infinite-resources&quot;&gt;2. Infinite resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfectionism is a beast that consumes significant resources for minimal gain. Resources can come in the form of time, money, and labor. When perfectionists have access to unlimited resources, they can strive for perfection without pushback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;perfectionism-in-the-real-world&quot;&gt;Perfectionism in the real world&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfectionists truly shine when given attainable goals and unlimited resources. Unfortunately these conditions won’t always be met in the real world. This is &lt;a href=&quot;/feeling-lost-after-graduation/&quot;&gt;one of the many challenges new graduates face when adjusting from school to work&lt;/a&gt;. Perfectionists must manage their urge to perfect as it may not be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;school-systems-reward-perfectionism&quot;&gt;School systems reward perfectionism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;School is one of the few situations where the two conditions are present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grading systems provide a metric that clearly defines perfection, making it attainable. This is particularly true for objective courses. An example of this would be math tests. Grading systems deem that 100% is the perfect score and is earned by correctly answering all the questions on the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students are also effectively given unlimited time to complete their work. Schoolwork is expected to be completed on the student’s own time. While it’s not healthy, overachievers can sacrifice their leisure time and pull all-nighters for that perfect score. Whether it’s to ace an exam or submit a flawless essay, they can keep working right up until the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;workplaces-punish-perfectionism&quot;&gt;Workplaces punish perfectionism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the workplace is not as friendly for perfectionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfection is much harder to achieve in the workplace. Since perfection is defined subjectively, perfectionists often don’t know when to throw in the towel. Moving goalposts are also common, which makes perfection even harder to attain. Without concrete and well-defined goals to work with, perfectionists will work tirelessly towards perfection but may never reach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As progress approaches perfection, additional effort tends to suffer from diminishing returns. Workplace budgets likely won’t tolerate their team pouring time and money for minimal returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-perfectionists-transition-from-school-to-work&quot;&gt;A perfectionist’s transition from school to work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student, perfectionism may have been an advantage. However, perfectionism can hamper your success in many real-world situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workplace, blowing the project budget is heavily looked down upon. This is especially true if you’re overspending the budget on inconsequential improvements. Meanwhile, your boss or client may not even appreciate the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also common to juggle multiple projects at once, dividing your attention. This makes it difficult to focus on even one project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing how it can affect your performance is an important step to overcoming perfectionism. We must shed our perfectionist tendencies that had been praised in school and acknowledge that the real world plays by different rules. In the workplace, we must look beyond the minute details and ration our resources efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 12:56:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/why-perfectionist-students-struggle-in-the-workplace/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/why-perfectionist-students-struggle-in-the-workplace/</guid>
        
        <tag>Wellness</tag>
        
        <tag>Growing Up</tag>
        
        
        <category>School Survival</category>
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Ace Technical Engineering Interviews</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every engineering job requires different sets of technical skills and experiences. Employers use technical interviews to assess and scope out their best job candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally all engineering job candidates, regardless of seniority, will be technically assessed. Despite this, even the most experienced engineers can get tripped up during technical interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-interview-guide-for-engineers&quot;&gt;Technical interview guide for engineers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-brush-up-on-engineering-fundamentals&quot;&gt;1. Brush up on engineering fundamentals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An engineer often relies on their understanding of fundamental concepts to solve problems. Technical interviews are an opportunity to showcase your familiarity with these concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now don’t go dusting off your old textbooks just yet. In most interviews, advanced concepts will not be tested. Instead, understand the relevant areas of focus and nail down the basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are relevant areas of focus? Which technical topics should you prepare for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order of priority, technical topics should be prepared if they are relevant to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The job description&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous projects listed on your resume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Industries the company specializes in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a lot of topics to prepare for. Don’t worry, it’s not as many as you think. Overlap between these topics is to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you may have studied the concepts many moons ago, interview anxiety can freeze up even the most seasoned engineers. Don’t overlook the importance of preparation. Knowing the basic concepts like the back of your hand can keep you cool and collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-know-your-audience&quot;&gt;2. Know your audience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before answering any technical questions, assess your audience, and adjust your language to fit their level of technicality. There are three levels of technicality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expert&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;informed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can encounter all three types of audience members during technical interviews, so &lt;a href=&quot;/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/&quot;&gt;adapt your technical language accordingly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers and line managers are typically informed or experts on the technical topic. HR managers tend to align better with a general audience, though they are usually briefed on some jargon and context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-understanding-the-styles-of-technical-assessments&quot;&gt;3. Understanding the styles of technical assessments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical interviews are comprised of one or more technical assessments. While there is an endless number of assessments, all assessments can be boiled down into three main styles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short-answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explanation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technical-assessment-styles-in-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;Each style has a different goal and challenges the candidate differently.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations challenge the candidate to present complex concepts. Short-answer questions quiz the candidate’s knowledge. Explanation questions gauge critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To perform well in these technical interviews, it’s crucial to understand what the interviewers are looking for in each assessment style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-keep-it-short-and-simple&quot;&gt;4. Keep it short and simple&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineers can grasp very complex concepts, but many have trouble concisely conveying their knowledge. It’s important to know what you’re talking about, but delivery is equally as important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s common for engineers to get caught up in details when explaining their thoughts. It’s tempting to go down the rabbit hole, droning on and on about specific technical details. Unfortunately, this can make even the brightest engineers appear incoherent and disorganized. Remember, brevity is the soul of wit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some technical interview types like presentations also have a set time limit. You must stay within their guidelines. Engineers who go over the time limit severely hurt their chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-admit-what-you-dont-know&quot;&gt;5. Admit what you don’t know&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a technical question stumps you, it’s okay to admit that you don’t know. Managers prefer honesty to overconfidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However just because you don’t know, doesn’t mean you can’t take an educated stab at it. Using engineering fundamentals, sometimes it is possible to work your way through the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you’re completely stumped, this approach should always be taken. It’s often more impressive, as it shows off your critical thinking. Make sure you explain your thought processes out loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A general format you can follow is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“That’s a tough question that I don’t know the answer to. However, based on my understanding of […], I know that […], thus my educated guess would be […].”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what happens, remember to ask for the answer they’re looking for. Not only is this a learning opportunity, but it also shows the interviewers that you’re eager to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 23:56:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technical Assessment Styles in Engineering Interviews</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Technical interviews gauge a job candidate’s technical skills. Every engineering jobs require different skills, and so every interview is unique. Despite this, all technical interviews are essentially a series of assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, every assessment can be categorized into one of the three styles, each with its advantages and disadvantages. It’s common for interviewers to use a combination of assessments at various interview stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-technical-assessments-styles&quot;&gt;The three technical assessments styles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In technical engineering interviews, assessments can be boiled down to one of the three styles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short-answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explanation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes each style unique is its goal and how it challenges the candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical presentations assess how well a candidate can express complex, technical topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations for technical interviews:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are assigned ahead of time, a few days before the interview&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually have a set time limit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes offer flexible with the technical topic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May require visual aids such as a slide deck or pamphlet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are given the freedom, choose topics that you are very familiar with, such as previous projects. This is because follow up questions are almost always part of the presentation and you need to be comfortable with your topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of presentation-style assessments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are assigned a case study and must present your findings during the interview&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are asked to prepare a presentation on a technical topic of your choice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are must design a solution for a given problem and propose it as an elevator pitch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-answer&quot;&gt;Short-answer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short-answer questions are purely knowledge-based questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are like trivia because they have a “you-know-it-or-you-don’t” element to it. If you don’t know the answer right away, you won’t be able to answer it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are often asked by non-technical interviewers. Answers can easily be verified with the help of an answer key provided by their technical colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the interviewers who ask these questions are often technically unqualified, short-answer questions can be very frustrating for several reasons. For one, if there are ambiguities in the question, the candidate can rarely ask for clarification. Also, in the rare case where the answer key is incorrect, it would be difficult to correct the interviewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While short-answers are quick and simple, they are not the best judge of one’s technical abilities. Thus, heavy reliance on short-answer technical questions should be &lt;a href=&quot;/red-flags-in-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;considered a red flag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of short-answer-style assessments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What is the definition of […]?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“List 3 examples of […]?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What is the keyboard shortcut for the command […]?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What does the acronym […] stand for?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;explanation&quot;&gt;Explanation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation questions gauge critical thinking and the ability to work under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This style has both elements of presentation-style and short-answer-style. Similar to a presentation, these questions require you to go in more detail about a technical topic and may come with follow up questions. Like the short-answer questions, the topic is not given ahead of time so you will need to draw from the knowledge you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of explanation question can range anywhere from hypothetical case studies to details on your resume. The special thing with explanation questions is that there often isn’t one right answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When answering these questions, walk through your thought process out loud. Many times, the interviewers will guide you in the right direction or question your thought process if you’re straying too far from the main point. For advanced technical questions, writing down details can help a lot as well. Don’t be scared to jot down the question, many interviewers will encourage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of explanation-style assessments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are given a problem and must write the solution out on a whiteboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What was the most challenging problem you solved while working on the […] project?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“What material would you recommend for […] and why?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 23:32:21 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/technical-assessment-styles-in-engineering-interviews/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/technical-assessment-styles-in-engineering-interviews/</guid>
        
        <tag>Interview</tag>
        
        
        <category>Job Search</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Audience Expertise Categories in Technical Communication</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re writing a client report, selling yourself during an &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-ace-technical-engineering-interviews/&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt;, or presenting to executives, understanding your audience’s technical level is crucial for technical communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When conveying technical information, some audiences require more definition and simplification than others. To communicate effectively, technical language needs to be tailored to the audience’s technical level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;in-content-ad&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;!-- In Content --&gt;
    &lt;ins class=&quot;adsbygoogle&quot; style=&quot;display:block&quot; data-ad-client=&quot;ca-pub-4004679572164789&quot; data-ad-slot=&quot;7791301556&quot; data-ad-format=&quot;auto&quot; data-full-width-responsive=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
         (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
    &lt;/script&gt;

    
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-types-of-technical-audiences&quot;&gt;The three types of technical audiences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, there are three levels of technical audiences: expert, informed, and general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;expert-audience&quot;&gt;Expert audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expert audiences have been formally trained on the technical topic. They are interested in details and require little to no concept definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of expert-level language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MPPTs were connected in parallel with the PV cells.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OPGW offer both the capability of grounding and high-speed data transmission.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The DAQ relied on Type K thermocouples for temperature readings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers, subject matter experts, and engineers can be found in this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;informed-audience&quot;&gt;Informed audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informed audiences are familiar with the technical topic, but may not have worked with it directly. They already have a grasp of the basic concepts, but may require explanations for advanced concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of informed-level language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maximum power point trackers were installed in parallel with the photovoltaic cells.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optical ground wires offer both lightning protection and data transmission along overhead power lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data acquisition system relied on transducers for temperature measurements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clients, executives, line managers, project managers, and engineers can be found in this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-audience&quot;&gt;General audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General audiences have no specialized knowledge of the technical topic. They work better with simplified ideas and clearly defined concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of general-level language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronics that optimize power output were installed with the solar panels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special cables can protect overhead power lines from lightning strikes while supporting telecommunications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data recorder relied on sensors for temperature measurements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human resource managers, accountants, and administration can be found in this category.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 20:11:32 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/audience-expertise-categories-in-technical-communication/</guid>
        
        <tag>Communication</tag>
        
        
        <category>Workplace Tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
